live streaming
is on
welcome everyone
my name is wasabi research club
today we have a special episode for you
because we are
you're cut off i guess
you got cut off adam yes i
realized i started the intro
anyway i feeling livestreaming is on now
or do i
the stream is on yes yes it is on
i just checked all right welcome
everyone this is the
money yes wasabi research club and today
we have a special episode for you
because we have a collaboration with
between many
guys and
and i i think uh
we are going to just mess around until
more people come and
start this these
the real show
in 15 minutes is that correct
yeah i guess
we'll just give people some time to drop
in but you can also
already say hello introduce yourself if
you like
how you found bitcoin or what interests
you about the topic today
can you guys hear me now or did i cut
off again
i didn't hear anything from you
in the last minute
yes so i was just saying that we are
going to wait until
until 15 minutes right
roughly 15 minutes to go
in the meantime let's talk about some
fun stuff like
what's the point of life
how's your job in mcdonald's did they
get you back
dropping mcdonald's uh yeah
right
we all have to work in at mcdonald's
again
not if you have invested your steers
into bitcoin
what was that not
if you have invested your spirit into
bitcoin
cool
what is
yeah i will still give people time to
drop in
can you hear me yes we can hear you
whoever nice thanks
but to introduce yourself say hello
we are still waiting for a little bit
for people to drop in and
hi thanks for setting this up i just um
heard from it
like three days ago uh through a
telephone group
in uh the podcast 21 someone somebody
shared it
and i'm really excited for it because i
just
uh wanted to dive a little deeper into
the topic of austrian economics
to understand the uh
like um how it changes
an economy to use these different
principles
and i'm really excited
cool
it's really hot here in vienna i don't
know oh it's like where you are at
yeah we also had like right let's talk
about the weather
yeah we had where we had hot days but
but now it's rainy
yesterday and today but maybe it's the
right weather for
an event like this yeah i just wanted to
explain why i may be sweating
yeah that's not the bitcoin price
okay it's cold and dark here in the moon
i think we should probably adapt to the
weather in el salvador so that we
should get used to these temperatures
that was that was for example
that was for example from speaking who
is in vr so
for example but you can see the
him only in a bit in the distance here
so
okay but it's it's
it's a it's just a two two weight bridge
yeah ah yes now
you can send some smiley if you
yes i can see that thanks for smiling
nice to see someone here in the audience
otherwise it looks a bit sad this summer
stage
what do you mean sad
like the party is happening elsewhere
yeah
but i maybe
yeah it depends but it depends better
where the speaker is right
i can i can fly around here a bit oh
cool yeah that's nice some action
that's great
yeah but so there's no no one on the
stage
no the the uh the gypsy drone or
stage for the r ride
um yeah yeah um the microphone in vr
meanwhile works so if the drone is in
front of the microphone then everybody
can hear you everywhere
oh no it's not quite working yet
and i tried to make it work but but
but there's another problem right now
with
i don't want to get into detail there's
there's now some kind of other problem
with
that has to do with blender and
exporting stuff it's yeah
okay what's your experience so far with
using the hubs for
meetings um yeah
i didn't know you're you're interested
in that so that's cool um maybe
we should we should have tried that
route
but but but but yeah it's um i think
some people have
it's for some people it's it's too
unusual i think
they they also replace some instruction
at the entry
which keyboard which keys to use to move
and all this kind of stuff some
you can see some people get lost they
don't move at all
or maybe they don't have a machine
that's powerful enough
so and we also get some negative
responses about this that
the people don't know how to use it also
we
do give some instruction explanations so
uh so yeah so i guess video conference
is easier but but why not both so we're
doing both
but but of course it plays a role where
the main speaker is if he's in the video
or in or in the vr world so
definitely today we are a second lost
citizen
but but it's it's it's it's really
really nice because
i mean i'm not so much into personally
into into
vr itself but for virtual meetings that
you have this special audio thing right
you can
you can have many groups talking yeah
but that's how they can read it right
um no no that's uh that's that's that is
activated
um so people could spread around
and and and talk about different things
at the same time
what's just currently not working is
that
there's a stage and a microphone which
should be louder than anything else
and that particular thing right now is
not it's not really working but
but yeah so people
can just come closer
i think it could be a nice option for
for
um for meetings and stuff
if um by default of course it's it's uh
there are a lot of um it's not sorry i
mean if
you want to if you want to do it more in
a professional settings then you
would have to run your own hubs cloud
instance which you
adapt a little bit so that people don't
use
all these cartoony avatars maybe
so yeah has anyone used the vr headset
to participate um definitely uh um
generally they're in in the bitcoin
world in bitcoin there are a lot of vr
events where people use that
um
but but but this particular thing that
we use here with nutella
we use because it's open source and it
works with just a web link
and there are people occasionally do use
a vr headset i personally don't
but but i think it's it's also a good
good a good option to just use it
as a desktop thing it's also it's also
very
very great i think because of this these
special audio features that i mentioned
i think the main advantage of using vr
is that you have hands
in uh in hubs then as well so you can
point somewhere
if you just use it on your laptop you do
not have hands
yeah but i think that's a minor detail
but at that point
as a small feedback i just tested it
in the web browser and it was pretty
intuitive so it was easy to use for me
yeah yeah cool some people find it very
good and intuitive to use it
especially i guess if you're already
used to gaming or something like that
but but yeah but some people also can
also get lost or don't have a
machine that's powerful enough so okay
yeah probably
as soon as i saw you can control with
wasd
i felt at home yeah yeah definitely
yes and you can look around with your
mouse like you know from all ego
shooters that's
quite perfect and if you have a laptop
that's capable of
hosting ego shooters then hubs works
extremely smooth but if you have a very
old and
outdated laptop it's very bumpy
yeah boyfriend but the particular
question i think you do have a vr
headset but
but you prefer to use desktop
i guess right so maybe you can answer
the questions
yes uh yeah well the b of the r
headsets have the usual problems of vr
it's a headset sometimes you get some
motion sickness after some hours
or depending on what you do and uh
well when you are on the laptop you just
see a screen and you can read somewhere
on another screen and whatever you like
so yeah
but i heard also that's a copy that's
because of when the frame rate is too
low so maybe we
with our previous meetups we used scenes
that are too complex or something like
that
uh we could play continue to play around
so we can
just wanted to say i prefer for meetings
so
or for talk or talking to other people i
prefer to
use the vr but for for presentations
it's a little bit uh
if you're stuck in vr for an hour and
looking
uh in front of on a presentation it's a
little bit
uh yeah it's it's it's
uh yeah not so fun okay yeah
i mean virtual events i think
uh nobody found the perfect solution yet
and you
see all sort of discussions about this
yeah but anyway i think we can we can
start now
more officially so so welcome today to
our meetup
um co-hosted with the wasabi
research club
if you want to enjoy
virtual meetups every week you can you
can also
find them with this link you see in the
chitty
at the wasabi research link do you want
to introduce yourselves
again for the for our record um
adam or anybody else from from the
wasabi team
yes welcome guys so this is the wasabi
research club
joint session with the bitcoin munich
community and our special
guest here is raheem
um um i don't think i don't want to both
share your name
so welcome hi
from i i also
i also planned to not
to not have to pronounce it i would have
just said
hello
all right so we are going to talk about
austrian economics and proxiology today
and i believe you guys would like to
also talk about some current topics
in the context of these these
fields of science so i'm looking forward
to it
thanks okay so okay yeah
let's go ahead and um do you want to
introduce yourself
perhaps okay sure i can introduce myself
no problem so this is my last name but
don't worry too much about it
it's originally from iran i've grown up
in austria
and i've grown up and studied mostly in
austria
without really hearing much about the
austrian school of economics and
it was only in the united states that i
learned that it was still a living
tradition
and i found
the last teachers of that tradition who
were still passing it on
and one in the united states one then
when i came back to europe
in germany and i've become an economist
after school i started out
in my career in natural sciences and
technology and it's
but have shifted
a bit and it was quite fitting because
the austrian school of economics
traditionally is a very
interdisciplinary approach
to understanding complex social
phenomena
i had an institute in vienna it's called
scolarium and i had a foundation
in switzerland called the free private
cities foundation
that i've assumed the presidency there
only
recently i've been teaching at
universities throughout europe for
already quite a while about 15 years now
and yeah i i think that the austrian
school as a
tradition of economics in the very
general sense
is underrated is quite relevant and it's
worth it to pass on
that tradition so there was a little
introduction
i'm not sure if i continue right ahead
or you want to say something else about
the meet up
yeah thanks for your introduction um
i was told you you want to do some kind
of freestyle presentation or we would
do it more interactive with
questions from the audience here and
there i guess everybody can
just mute yourself at any time if you
have question
questions but please also um
watch that you are muted when you when
you don't want to speak up
we are always still have problems
sometimes the people don't
mute themselves properly um
yeah so but then where do we start
at which topic um we some kind of teaser
i guess
the bitcoin world moves so fast last
week it was the odd news about el
salvador now it's
it's already a bit uh it feels already
long ago but maybe we should use it
um i might as i saw on your twitter
stream that you that you
that you have quite nuanced to you is
about about this
actually so you don't you're not
cheerleading this
um like most bitcoiners do um
so maybe you would want to go want to go
a little bit
into this yes uh
i mean it's about politics mostly and
politics has two layers really there's
the hidden layer which is coercion and
the public layer which is usually pr so
economics on the other hand tries to
understand
uh what's happening and uh the also the
approach of the austrian school was to
try it in a very value neutral way
so without cheerleading or without too
much moralizing and antagonizing
what you don't like even if you don't
like what you're seeing
so i don't think that's really a shift
in economic policy than el salvador
and we shouldn't read too much into it i
think it was only a question of time
until uh one country which is not
clearly aligned with either the us
or china as we're getting into a more
multi-polar
world is
may use me use bitcoin adoption in a
sense to present
itself and to get some attention as well
it's a tech savvy and young president
so i'm i i think it's a positive step
for the country and the people there i
think it's happened in el salvador
because there
was this philanthropic long-term project
of bitcoin beach
which i'm generally sympathetic towards
what
has been tried there and what has been
achieved so far
and i think mostly for el salvador it
means attracting
investors of this industry and other
countries have tried before with this
kind of
uh crypto valley style
uh getting attention from crypto
investors
and then also crypto tourists of bitcoin
tourists
and detention and so on so i think
generally is understandable it's not the
kind of conspiracy needed to explain why
uh that step was taken by this president
and uh
if you like him you'd say he's very
popular if you dislike him you'd say
he's very populist
generally he's in the style of the more
authoritarian
latin american presidents
i don't know him personally i'm quite
very and skeptical towards politics in
general
as i think i made clear by
thinking that most of publicly known
policies are in the field of pr which
means
rationalizing legitimizing things that
are already there so
i think usually uh that's not the cause
of change
and i don't think that bitcoin needs
countries
adopting it and it would rather harm for
bitcoin
the perception of it really being a
non-sovereign
money that would somehow now need
ambassadors and would need
political endorsements and so on and it
would lend to a kind of misunderstanding
potentially
so i i wouldn't read too much into it i
i don't think there's a need for a lot
of cheerleading
but again one can be friendly towards
that
change as symptomatic of
bitcoin offering um for many people a
potential
alternative to uh other currencies or
assets
uh and in particular the geopolitical
dimension
of bitcoin uh we've seen that uh
again and again that uh
countries really are challenged of
course in this kind of u.s
let order in having the sovereignty of
the their
funds we've seen that with countries
that have gold reserves
even blocked or potential
potentially it's quite important how the
us sees
the official government as we've seen
with venezuela
and of course if you like it or not that
leads to a tendency
of countries to look for more sovereign
in the sense but if you are not a strong
military power it
must mean a kind of non-sovereign assets
which means they are not controlled by
the location where they are stored at
they are not the currency of a major
power but something in between
and of course many of the reasons uh
governments that are not aligned with
one of those blocks
needs assets and need to move assets
are usually bad i mean a lot of it is
just shifting wealth out of the country
uh because uh for for
the politicians or their families or
their friends
so it's a way to even siphon off
from a country but in that case of el
salvador what's really
the most positive thing is that there's
a popular need
uh due to the remittances so that the
major
reason to move assets across the country
uh its remittances it's one of those
latin american countries is really
dependent on remittances and the
legacy infrastructure for remittances is
terrible
so there's really an obvious advantage
of using
bitcoin or other cryptocurrencies but we
can discuss that uh
later on definitely there is a need for
improvements on the legacy solutions so
that's why
i think generally it's a positive
dynamic
that's been going on but i tried to
distinguish a little bit between the
political side and the economic side
so i don't think that's it's really the
question of bitcoin
becoming the money in el salvador uh
it's always the question of course what
money is but i
i tend to not find that very interesting
um
i think bitcoin has proved itself to be
a financial asset
uh and a rather resilient financial
asset
so i i don't see a shift in economic
policy nothing really revolutionary
there in the sense of economic policy
if they go further um i i think it will
be in trying to present
el salvador as a destination for mining
um
and probably a kind of crypto valley in
latin america
and that doesn't have too much
impact on economic policy and again it's
not clear that there's
a lot of freedom in economic policy
most countries are integrated in the
kind of economic order
and financial system that we have
countries not well integrated there
really have economic problems
and so it's
really hard and people who see in
bitcoin
or other cryptocurrencies a possibility
to uh have a new kind of financial
system economic system
either tend to over hype this potential
that already using the technology brings
your kind of utopian
new economic order or get angry about
and frustrated about bitcoin
and thus rather look for other
cryptocurrencies other projects
in seeing that potential fulfilled
and there's really kind of utopian
longing of course for a different order
and i think first of economics
is there a bit in between uh it has been
from the beginning quite critical
from towards the modern financial system
but at the same time it's not utopian
it's not trying to construct a new order
it's mostly trying to understand what's
going on
and this field is so complicated that it
doesn't really stop i mean once you
think you've understood it it has
already evolved and changed
quite a lot so of course the financial
system
uh has changed a lot since the 19th
century
and but the 19th century already was a
time of dynamic
uh change
which surpassed the understanding of
most people and mostly colonists of
course as well
so i try to keep up with developments
and then no one can really anticipate
where it's going but i don't think it
was too surprising
that one country i would have pinpoint
to a country that's not
aligned with either dollar sphere
or the potentially emerging chinese
sphere
to either see bitcoin as a potential
asset for the central bank's
bank balance sheet
or yes a government reserve
in effect and we will have yet to see if
el salvador already goes there
having government reserves or central
bank reserves in bitcoin so far i think
it's mostly trying to present itself as
a bitcoin friendly destination
uh and already that's positive of course
with the influx of potential investors
and tourists but of course it has a
negative side of attracting potential
scammers and hustlers
of which the cryptocurrency field is
rife
so i i hope that
this kind of top-down political process
uh does not vote ill uh for the general
understanding and adoption of bitcoin
uh and really have to reiterate the
positive thing is this kind of
more bottom-up emergence
it's not entirely bottom-up it is an
entrepreneurial
philanthropic social entrepreneurial
project there
uh which i think is one of the best ways
to
try out something new offer it to people
voluntarily
see if it works try to focus on
education and technology and not so much
on the legal side
of it and i think it was the positive
example that led to
this kind of bitcoin maximalist stance
there even which
may seem a bit surprising that it's
specifically bitcoin
and even the trough for the law sees
a kind of obligations or really
interprets legal tender in a quite
strict sense
of being obliged to accept payment
in bitcoin
so should i try myself to make the
bridge to
uh the austrian school and its economic
theory or will you
or do you want to just hit or continue
with another question
yeah i guess if something disagrees as
well
yes maybe somebody has questions in the
audience
so please feel free to speak up
so i don't have a question because i
pretty much agree with everything and
you know it's really
really not always that that someone is
talking about for a topic for like
uh 10 minutes and and there isn't
anything i would disagree with i would
just
have one comment is that i
think it's they are not obliged
to to accept cryptos
it was in the in the ruling or
for the proposal but uh where
politicians then came out and said that
it is
it is not required for them to to accept
so
you know just wanted to throw that in
yeah
yeah i i don't think that the final law
will have that but the
the draft i'd seen had the it was
paragraph seven uh it had that
obligation
uh in it uh of course not an obligation
to keep
bitcoin but to accept it and the
government would provide the technology
if you're not able to to
to exchange it immediately into dollar
so but but i think yes i don't know
maybe you know something else or
something new i mean that could change
any minute uh
what the definitive law would look like
i don't know i've only seen the draft
yes certainly
all right so does anyone have any
questions
and then i guess let's move on to the
austrian school of economics
and proxiology which is
like a topic that i never read a phone
but
but whenever anyone was talking about it
it was really interesting
so you had to get this already in your
research club few months ago i saw it
yeah yeah it just i've it's been
explained many times but
never read upon that's my point
okay yeah maybe
would be cool if you could give some
kind of
overview i am also i guess it's
difficult
like what is bitcoin yeah
yeah yeah it's difficult because it's a
different thing to different people so
it's the same answer
for bitcoin as for the austrian school
of economics
most people tend to associate the
austrian school of economics with an
ideology so it's become
mainly in in the u.s become a label
for a kind of sub-class maybe of
libertarianism
and i consider it as
a scientific tradition
but there's already a contradiction
in terms it's not entirely clear how
it's a tradition i'll try to explain
that because it broke with a lot of
traditions and it's not entirely clear
that it's a science
and i'll start with that point so
uh it emerged in the 19th century uh
with the
writings of carl menger and vienna
at the time was the center of a large
empire
in eastern central europe
and there was a kind of belated
enlightenment happening there it
was a time of very rapid
industrialization
and very rapid wealth explosion a bit
like in asia today
it was first germany and then it passed
on to uh
rather not the german austrian parts of
today but bohemia
and moravia and so on so important parts
of the
austrian empire and
in particular in the city which was
administered capital and and the capital
where the emperor was living but also a
hub
of exchange and and the hub of finance
and uh there is a certain kind of
enlightenment happened like the scottish
enlightenment before
um and which is quite distinct from the
french enlightenment
in the scottish enlightenment as in the
austrian enlightenment
you had a very interesting mix of
economic practitioners of entrepreneurs
and merchants and
bankers and social scientists
in the kind of exchange between them so
there was this kind of salon atmosphere
the coffee shops
uh uh people having the wealth
and also the leisure to empty interest
to try to ask questions about society
and trying to understand what's going on
because there all these dynamic shifts
dynamic changes the austrian empire
moved rapidly within a generation from a
very
agrarian
monarchy not entirely but
within its hubs it became a modern
industrialized
place and vienna was full of
contradictions at the time and
one of the reasons is that you have this
self-accelerated development of
technology
being adopted so that's one part of
industrialization it means you apply
technology to production and
with the receipts with the income you
get from that you
increase the capital and you are able to
deploy technology
fairly quickly if you are able to
accumulate that kind of capital
so it's really a self-driving process
once it's gone
once it's going and for a while there
was
quite friendly circumstances of the
authorities being friendly towards that
kind of development
because of course the military
importance of it was seen as
in in the united states a little bit
later
that industrialization would be
important so
it was a short time where entrepreneurs
had a lot of freedom
in austria but unfortunately
we inherited from the british as most of
the world not only this tradition of
industrial revolution as it's called
it's a misnomer it's a bit misleading
but
that kind of capital financed
technological
deployment on a large scale plus the
innovations in finance
from the british more or less
and one part of this innovation is that
you monetize
government debt and
you have a more flexible way of looking
at money and a lot of it becomes
fiduciary media that's the term
by one of the greatest theories of the
austrian school lubric for mises
it's what we now always would call fiat
but it's not meant in a normative sense
it means fiduciary
means there's a lot of trust involved
and
a lot of it doesn't really materialize
it's like
uh in ledger's and and uh people
increase
credit mostly um and have a maturity
mismatch and so on so there are a lot of
details there
the mix of that financial innovation
if you have it at the same time as the
introduction of
the new capital-based technological
breakthroughs you have an
increased acceleration which is too fast
for most people
and leads to distortions as well they
are already having a hard time
keeping trace and track of the
technological changes
and those kind of financial
those financial innovations in
particular based
on on government pursuing industrial
policies
leads to a kind of over inflation of
the change in the production structure
and you get a lot of
counter reaction of the population so
you have
a movement which produces wealth but at
the same time leads to very quick
distortions
of the societal order and you get a lot
of political counter reactions so vienna
was ripe
of ideologists of every kind so at the
same coffee shop
you had a young hitler meter young
trotsky even stalin was there you had a
sigmund freud there trying to look at
the unconscious
so it was really crazy time and almost
all the crazy
and unfortunately terrible
ideas of the time were present
at the vietnamese coffee shop but also a
tradition of trying to understand the
dynamics of what was going on
and that's the austrian school of
economics i'd say it's part of the
austrian enlightenment
and it's a kind of
rare bridge between practical
understanding and practical economics
and theory which goes really
deep in the sense of epistemologies
really trying to think about where
knowledge comes from
what methods you use to understand
knowledge and
and uh what was really revolutionary
about the insight
of carl menger and then his students
later on
uh in particular then how he came back
to this idea was
understanding that there's a new kind of
quality emerging
and that's out of the complexity of
society so society gets more and more
complex
and that needs new methods of
understanding it's you can't use the old
mechanical ways of looking it you can't
use the old mercantilist
ways of looking uh as a country at the
country as just
basically a household that some
authority figure
controls as you would control a company
or or a household
but it's a complex emergent
order which looks as more bottom-up
processes
feedback loops a lot of that was then
discovered only in the last
generation in the natural sciences but
here the social sciences refers
first in understanding that this kind of
complexity
needs a new epistemology and
what was also understood is that the
natural sciences of the time
uh which were perceived as very powerful
of course
as they still are today because they
seem to
help understand the technological
revolutions
happening at the time and the
understanding was you can't really
transpose
those kind of methods to the social
sciences
you can't look at people as if there
were particles
and hope to understand what's going on
the only way to really understand is to
have an emphatical approach
and that's where the subjectivism of the
austrian school comes in so really
looking through the eyes
of the economic agents and trying to
understand what their subjective ends
are
and why they are trying to use the means
they are trying to use to achieve those
ends and
it's a kind of bottom-up approach to
understanding very complex phenomena
you start with the economic agent and
you try to find out what's
what are universal aspects of human
nature
and one of these universal aspects is
that human beings are
able to act they are not just reacting
it's not just their
instincts that are always telling them
what to do
uh it's not just kind of biological
memory
happening there but human beings
feel themselves in situations of choice
and decision making
where they have to weigh alternatives
and where they really have to rank their
alternatives
and uh that proves quite challenges to
challenging to human beings but
adds another layer of complexity to
social phenomena because we watch each
other
we learn from each other we try to
imitate each other
and of course there's a huge
diversity in the patterns of our kind
which are shaped by culture but are
always interacting with each other
and it's this very down-to-earth
approach to economics which has proved
to be quite fruitful
and already manga was very unusual
for an economist he started out as a
journalist
covering what was really happening on
the exchange on the stock exchange
and he was very young when he wrote
his major treaties and then he became
the tutor of the crown prince
unfortunately crown prince
killed himself so he
would not be put in the position of
being emperor
later on otherwise the impact would have
been even larger of the austrian school
uh a lot of most of the students of karl
menger
came into very high position within the
monarchy but of course the monarchy
didn't survive for long
and with the monarchy falling after the
monarchy falling it didn't take too long
for europe to be falling
and europe basically self-destructed and
most uh
intellectual traditions became cut off
in europe and most representatives of
the austrian school
moved abroad many already before the
nazis took over
or in the course of them taking over
and uh a large part moved to the united
states they moved elsewhere as well but
it was in the united states that
it reestablished itself as a living
tradition
and the tradition was a tradition is you
have a teacher and a student
link and
this link means that it's a
it's a certain way of looking at the
world it doesn't mean that you follow a
guru it's not like a religion
and usually there's a lot of
disagreement between the student and the
teacher
but it's a link of transmitting i kind
of looking at the world
in society and there are few defining
characteristics but
it's not very clear-cut i i think what
was defining
uh at the term was that uh
the most important work of the austrian
school took place not in academia it was
in the salon
in coffee shop kind of atmosphere and it
was in circles that were
organized for example by mises and
baha'i
and others they had all these
interdisciplinary circles where the
brightest people of their time came
together and discussed
had really deep discussions about their
time but also about theory and in
particular epistemological theory
and you had practitioners and you have
theorists
of all very different disciplines
coming together and uh interestingly the
economic mainstream uh of course uh has
adopted as
most traditional and social sciences
more the approach of the inductive
sciences
of of the natural sciences the deductive
methods
the inductive methods of the natural
sciences which means
looking for data trying to extrapolate
laws or
modeling something
and so the academic academic tradition
of economics was a little bit astray i'd
say
a part of this academization was that
you have
disciplines that are separated from each
other
and that proved to be useful
for those disciplines where you really
have a lot of data gathering
and hard work as in the languages for
example
in translations in data gathering
and and so on where it's a lot of
division of labor
but it does really work in the more
interdisciplinary fields
because you can't separate the human
being into an economic
being and into a social being or a
political being
it's everything at the same time
so um i think academic or mainstream
economics
has taken a wrong term i don't think
it's useful at all
i don't think it's a science but because
i don't think that economics is
a science in the sense that we uh
uh give it a lot of authority because we
think there are some kind of laws and
there are experts who know these laws
and they can predict anything
empirically it's very rare
and it holds a very consistent result
that we get if you look at the data
is that economic data and economic
models
does not predict anything so it's safer
to roll the dice than to listen to
economists
usually they are wrong so they're more
often wrong than they are right
and so they even were worse than rolling
the dice
and it doesn't bode well now i wouldn't
say that austrian economists have a
crystal ball
uh it's not about that but they
understand why
they can't predict and being that humble
sometimes
they even have predictions that turn out
to be true because they're very general
and they're about understanding the
dynamics of something happening and not
being surprised
when you see that then roll out the way
you described it before and
so austrian economics usually has a very
hidden part of it the obvious part is
the ideological political leanings and
the academic
part of it and the hidden part is the
more practical influence of
the austrian school one of the most
important students of
calming was felix omari who
more or less was the founder of the
swiss private banking
which turned quite important in
particular then after the wars
and you had a lot of practitioners there
who behind the wheels behind the
curtains had a tremendous impact
so i think the influence of the austrian
school
is underrated and not really seen and i
think one of the influences of the
austin school was
in inspiring uh people to experiment
with different
uh monetary experiments and i think
bitcoin
is one of the results of these
inspirations
and it comes from a more critical
perception
analysis of the financial order is
developed
in a strong interest for monetary
phenomena
because interestingly mainstream
economics is
worst on the most interesting phenomena
money and entrepreneurship
because they are most complex and they
really
make it difficult to model something so
it's monetary theory
capital theory entrepreneurial theory
that's really not well developed in
mainstream economics
and that's where the austrian school is
really strong in comparison
and i mentioned before the most
important monetary theorist was lubric
for mises
with his treaties uh uh on money and
what he tried uh is to continue manga's
approach of having a very
bottom-up understanding of monetary
phenomena
not describing something as it is at the
moment
but understanding where it's coming from
and somehow
find the right terms to describe all
this huge diversity of monetary
phenomena
so it's it's an understanding that's one
of the most complex fields of human
interaction
uh monetary phenomena and it's really
trying to understand
its whole diversity and complexity
as a dynamic as a dynamic phenomenon not
as something static
not as something imposed as it is not as
something physical that we can look at
and everyone
says oh wow that's money we know it
because it says money on
printed on it now we want to understand
monetary phenomena is the arise
out of human action and
human beings seeking means to fulfill
their subjective ends
so any questions so far
so i i would like to just ask that
uh the chicago school and the austrian
school
do you know how if they are related and
if so
how or what are the differences
yeah it's really hard to say what's a
school it's not really clear-cut
but they fostered academic traditions
and
in the most important sense a group of
people adopting
a method certain methods because they
got them from
an important teacher and pass them on to
students they are more or less the
opposite of each other so it is
epistemologically they are very
different
the chicago school is much closer to the
mainstream in the sense it's a powerful
neoclassical
schools and epistemologically
it's uh milton friedman was quite
important
in that school and he said that
it's about modeling and the models have
to be false and we know that they are
false because we need to simplify
so i don't think it's evil i i think it
makes sense to say that
but the austrian school uh
went for a different approach so they
said no let's not try to simplify what
we're seeing
because it could be that we're missing
the most important things
so we don't want to do economics for a
homo economicals which means a
simplified
agent where we define his utility
function
and so on and then we can you use all
that
modeling that we know from mathematics
we could even have
systems of equations and so on
and the austrian school in particular
now
the praxiological path which was then
mostly developed because mises turned
out to be
uh the most important austrian who
lived and taught then in the united
states so he became quite crucial for
the survival of this tradition
as its own tradition other members of
the austrian school
more or less became part of the
mainstream
with a bit of different weights that
they put on things and and
it doesn't mean that they're entirely
wrong but it disappeared for them it
disappeared
as a different distinguishing tradition
i'd say
and some got pretty close high it got
pretty close to the chicago school there
was still some disagreement
but that was basically because hayek
more or less left
or thought that the economic questions
aren't the most interesting one so then
he focused later on psychological
questions and on questions of the
history of ideas and on questions of the
legal order
so he focused there and then basically
uh he thought it was not that important
at the time or for him not that
interesting to focus too much on the
epistemology
of economics as it should be and mises
remained quite strict in epistemological
questions
so there is no general agreement what
was the right path to take
those who followed the mission path
turned out to become more irrelevant for
academic economics
because the chicago school at least
can make use of uh more mathematical
methods
methods and it can be used to compare to
data so you can use it as
kind of comparing models to data
and schumpeter was very outspoken about
that
why why that's the way to go he said
well uh
politics needs numbers they need numbers
to
legitimize the interests that are there
because they need something to look
scientific
and of course uh if you really ask the
question
who is working as an economist and who
is paying for the economies that realize
that the demand for economists
is mostly demand for the rationalization
of
interests of hidden interests usually of
political interests
so you need some experts who put out
scientific looking stuff
which means either a lot of numbers or
equations or
charts to sell the policy that you want
to sell
and of course a good sign that that's
the case it's the most economies that
ever worked in the country worked in the
soviet union
so the one of the worst economies of the
time had the most economists
employed and that shows you
the turn that economics more or less has
taken
and it's not really the fault of
economists it's because
the complexity of social phenomena
which leads me to the understanding that
there isn't really something
such as economics and it's why mises and
then his followers his students
avoided the term economics they proposed
a different classification
and mises proposed to use the term
praxiology as the science of human
action as a very broad approach to
social sciences
and within this field the field of
catholictics
which is understanding phenomena of
exchange and
interaction between people in particular
foreigners who don't know and don't
trust each other
and it's that part that has the most
overlap
with economics as we understand it today
and i think it's a much sound approach
to it that you see it embedded in the
more general understanding of human
beings and the logic of human action
and then you look in particular in the
into the problems
of trustless exchange trustless
interaction
or interactions that has problems of
trust
and most people who react against
that kind of economic thinking or
catalactic thinking
are really have a problem with a modern
society where we mostly interact with
foreigners
and if you have a time where
the social order uh
changes very fast and suddenly you lose
your
social links that you're used to and you
you lose the kind of
legitimacy and hierarchy that you use to
uh
most people counteract towards death and
deceited as a
terrible change of society and they
blame
the people who are seemingly imposing
this shift on them
and that's where why there's a lot of
hatred against that
part in particular of economics which i
would call catalactics
and and of course monetary eth phenomena
are a part of catalytics
in particular and that's where there's a
lot of i'm this
misunderstanding and ideological
reaction against monetary phenomena
because they're typical of this kind of
catalytic order which is called a
catalytic
and it comes from the greek uh catalati
in means to exchange
okay so it's an exchange order you you
could call it
that was a really nice answer very much
in that uh and i would agree that the
strait was the main difference between
austrians and
chicago schools but um the more like the
conclusions that they draw
are similar in the terms of the general
market economy
like milton friedman's book choice is
very austrian
in some sense but where they disagree on
conclusions very much
is monetary economics right so your uh
treatment is much closer to fischer and
others that's a very good question now
there are two parts
the one is generally conclusions in the
sense of economic policy are overrated
and because
there's really a knowledge problem even
a proponent of the austrian school can't
really prescribe i mean i wouldn't dare
to prescribe
an economic policy for el salvador for
example
uh but i would even dare less to propose
that for
for the european union i think there's a
lot of over
estimating the kind of knowledge that
economic experts can have
so the approach to economic policy which
is most in agreement with the austrian
school of economics and its epistemology
is a kind of trial and error but uh
entrepreneurial trial era where you have
uh skin in the game
where you try to learn uh where you try
to adapt
as things change and you where you have
a lot of paradoxical
links in there not generally once the
austrian school
tends to be friendly towards the market
order
and i think it's really hard not to be
friendly towards the extended market
order
if you look at economic history
and most people don't do that they look
at history because they
try to find something that proves their
point of view so they're very selective
but if you look at economic history in
the sense of material well-being and the
change in material
well-being it's really impressive what
has happened and how exponential
the process is no matter what kind of
empirical data you look at
and usually austrian school doesn't look
that much
but i think it's important to look at
history how it really happened
and there you see that there's an
exponential dynamic happening
it's we haven't really managed to
explain it uh
very well uh but i think we're getting
there but most people
haven't really realized that there was
this dynamic revolution happening
and part of the revolution is that for
most of uh
human history most people lived like
their parents there was very little
change
in the professional patterns in the
channel level of valves it was very
gradual
and there was downturns and so on and
then only a few hundred years ago
basically in this uh you of course it
started before the trend but in
exponential functions you only see it
when it's already there when you're
already the last part and then you can't
stop it you can't change it anymore
and that happened in uh what we call the
industrial revolution which is a
misnomer because it was not at the point
it's just at the point where you see the
change but the change has happened
before of course
it's only when you see the
exponentiality of it so there was a
miracle of wealth creation
and it's still not obvious i think
to point more towards the technological
side of it and the innovations that were
necessary and i think it's a critical
mess of innovations that are necessary
so that they become self-sustaining and
self-accelerating
but on the same time we have a kind of
self-accelerating but very
bubbly very cyclical pattern of
financial innovation happening
and this cyclical nature was very well
understood
by the austrian economists and that's
the business cycle theory so they
understood that there's a cyclicality
which does not come from the technic
technological cycles because of course
there are technological cycles as well
but that was the understanding not of
schumpeter he's not really part of the
austrian school even though he
was a student of the austrian school but
he didn't pass it on as its own
tradition he shifted
and the mainstream approach more or less
thinks that the miracle of valve is
closely linked to the miracle of money
but it's meant the modern money in the
modern sense where basically you have
this effort of trying to control the
money supply
uh first by a bunch of banks and then
the central bank
as the market maker of the last resort
which has
made it much more complex so you have a
very dynamic situation and of course
there's something positive about it
and the positive thing is we approached
a global division of labor
which increased the valve potential a
lot
and uh i think it's hard not to be
positive about that
otherwise you'd roman you romantize
a lot the past and the past was really
harsh for most people
most children didn't survive until old
age
so i think there was really a tremendous
change in
living conditions for most people but it
was
accelerated and distorted in a way that
i dislike and i think explains a lot of
the counteraction towards a
modern economy which has then been
termed capitalism
uh which is an ideological term it
basically it meant in the 19th century
everything you don't like about modern
society call it capitalism and nowadays
it means everything you don't like about
21st century society
and of course there's a lot to dislike
in particular
in the economic order in the financial
system
because it's usually distorted it's
distorted in a sense that
inequality is increasing a lot without
the need so it's not really the
inequality increasing because
people do a better job than other people
that always be inequality of course
it's a kind of inequality because due to
the monetary distortions and it's kind
of accelerated and distorted inequality
and then distorted production structure
uh with a lot of symptoms that people
have a hard time understanding
and and project them into the market
order
i don't think there's an alternative to
going back from this extended market
order which means we
cooperate with foreigners mostly we
exchange
in a global division of labor our
capacity to produce value for other
people if we went
back to the old order of most people
never live leaving their village
and most people just interacting with in
a very small economic
uh unity uh the wealth would be so much
lower that
uh it would be too drastic exchange a
change for most people
and we'd have mass starvation uh and
mass misery
so i don't think there's really an
alternative so i think the
friendliness towards the market and
towards exchange between foreigners
is a kind of very value neutral
acceptance
of uh it's better to pre it's better
or most people prefer health to sickness
and most people prefer life
to death but with all the diversity of
values
uh so you should be free to pursue a
life
in minimalism and and without exchange
that should be possible but only an
extended
change order gives you both options the
option to withdraw from exchange and the
option to engage in exchange without
this extended order
you'd only have the option to withdraw
from
the larger extended exchange order and
the price
would be much too large for most people
to pay
so that's why the ocean school is
friendly towards the market
and it was adopted in the united states
of as a counter-reaction towards the
kind of new deal policies which led
towards
economic planning and
were unfriendly towards the market order
so there were ideological reasons of
course and
now getting back to milton friedman
milton friedman
became famous in a time where there was
a bit of counter-reaction towards this
government planning
people became a bit frustrated by the
big promises
of endless wealth and the reality of
politics
interventionism of the u.s government
showed itself abroad and uh within the
country
and it was a time that was friendly
towards more
uh ideas skeptical towards government
so milton friedman embarked on that he
was a very eloquent economist
he had the academic background and
legitimacy
and he got famous for his tv series
free to choose and
basically was explaining
for a general population why price
controls are a bad idea why economic
planning and rationing are a bad idea
and generally the spontaneous order of a
market
or explaining the spontaneous order of a
market in the change to general
population
now where milton friedman specialized as
an economist there's really the the
difference is very stark and uh milton
friedman was mostly a monetary economist
and he changed a lot over time so the
old fried men
more or less disavowed the younger
freedmen
so more or less at the end of his life
he approached the austrian school not in
a positive sense but in a negative sense
he became very skeptical
of central banks and of the idea
that it's possible based on economic
theory to have
experts run correct money supply and
monetary policies
and then he proposed to replace them by
an algorithm more or less so
that seems a bit prophetic but
so it's really hard to compare uh
friedman in the austrian school
uh as a tradition of monetary economics
it's more inductive it's based on data
but that's really problematic because
the
castle connections are so complex and
the process also complex that usually
data is misleading
and people everyone can select the data
he wants to select to rationalize his
own theory
and and having this data approach
at the time where you didn't have big
data and
extrapolating that in charts and makes
it look more scientific than it is
and that has tended to be very
misleading so
milton friedman is really to blame i i
would say for lending
credibility to the idea that you can
have experts
if they have enough data and good models
steer
as a kind of macro planning the whole
economy
and the approach of the austrian school
in in
in in its best or understood the best
way i think is much more humble
so he's claiming i yeah you shouldn't
even put that much power into the hands
of milton friedman and not even a ludwig
from mises
so when ludwig von mises was asked what
he would do as the
president of the central bank he would
say he would resign
and i i i think uh it's it's because
the rich responsibility is immense and
you really have to realize
even with the best intentions there's so
much complex paradoxical effects
you could trigger that it's really much
better to think about the long-term
resilience
than the short-term steering of monetary
policy
and that led hayek then to be very
prophetic in the sense he knew that
there'd be
there need to be experiments uh in
monetary in the monetary order
and we need to figure out ways but not
economists he thought he thought
entrepreneurs would figure out ways to
cope with the complexity
of a global extended order and what
monetary technology would be best to use
in that case
and could provide solutions for people
and means for people
because the monetary order was in
terminal of course after the abandoning
of the gold standard
and the solution
that was found uh was not in total
agreement with what uh
members of the austrian school would
have proposed or expected
uh and mostly the reason is that it was
all
based on economic experts with nobel
prizes and so on
and hayek was the only recipient of the
nobel prize who had
the speech he gave to thank for the
nobel prize he basically blamed
them that is a really bad idea to hand
out a nobel prize to economists
and i think that's a great way to answer
that
the nobel prize gave a kind of
legitimacy to economics as if it was a
natural science with
experts being engineers who are able to
steer
very complex phenomena and build
new technology but of course they are
not technologists
they are not even entrepreneurs they are
just academics
who usually don't have skin in the game
and don't have to bear the cost
if their ideas prove to be wrong
i hope he cleared up a little bit uh
where why there's some similarity about
general disagreement
uh between the friedman and the austrian
school
so yes definitely thank you and since
you talked about so much about me tom
friedman i
feel obliged to to to mention that
i actually had a discussion with david
fleetman
his son uh on the coming world of strong
privacy and uh and and maybe
maybe i would just like to ask if you
have heard about david and
and if yes then what kind of economist
he is
oh i know david friedman personally as
well and and
i have great respect for him i think
he's a great scholar
he's very different from his father not
that his father was evil i don't think
his father was evil it was just the
focus on academic economics
unfortunately david friedman has not
focused too much
on academic economics maybe one of the
reason is that like myself he has a
background in the natural sciences
and his approach to economics is
quite uh i i i'd say unusual
uh it's uh uh on the one side it's this
kind of
pop popularization of understanding
incentives so most
his books are on understanding
uh the role of incentives and
i think that's a bit over played maybe
from the epistemological side but it's
not important i think incentives are
important i think it's interesting
to look at the world through this lens
it's always the question i mean who's
got to
who gets to profit from something how
can you change circumstances
to improve dynamics so there's general
agreement with the austrian schools
epistemologically is a bit different but
that would be uh
too much going too much into detail
there uh and on the other hand he's
proved to be a tremendously important
legal scholar
looking into a legal traditions that are
different
from the legal mainstream as well i'd
say
uh so es hayek he
has the strongest interest i think in
phenomena of order
and in particular the legal order and
what it means where norms come from
uh what law can learn from economics and
what economics can learn from law
and so on so there's much more agreement
between david friedman
and the traditions of the austrian
schools so
and i think there won't be much
disagreement from himself
from his side he's very friendly towards
austrian economics and austrian
economists like myself tend to be very
friendly
towards david friedman um
there may be differences but then the
way i
uh define the austrian school of
economics i
i would count him among one of us
because it's interdisciplinary his
approach
it's not mainstream academic it's very
open-minded
different traditions and very empathic
in trying to understand with his focus
on incentives how
people subjectively try
to find means for their ends basically
and try to really ask yourself what are
the ends of people
why do they choose that means why do
they follow those norms uh or not
yeah and then of course his son again i
i know him as well
and have a different meeting ground
there his son petry friedman
has become a proponent of seasteading
and in particular the field that i'm now
in
the new industry that i'm in as well
the free private cities movement which
means
trying more or less to bring competition
to the industry of living together in
the kind of legal and political
arrangements
people choose and that's a really very
dynamic industry right now
uh where a lot of things are happening a
lot of very interesting projects are
happening and there's a lot of overlap
with the crypto community and in
particular the bitcoin community
where of course people had the
experience of uh
in the realm of bitcoin something
emerging out of the blue out of nothing
as a really a contender a contender
against the legacy systems
and getting that kind of traction
getting that importance
turns you very optimistic that that may
happen in other fields as well that if
you bring the same kind of innovation
that has been brought
to the financial sector into other
sectors we can expect
radically innovative and groundbreaking
uh revolutions there as well and they
are
i find a lot of common ground with padre
friedman
who is now part of the promos venture
capital fund
which is investing in exactly the kind
of industry that
the foundation that i am heading is
trying to prepare the crown for
i i i usually
in the very brief sense i'd say we try
to make bitcoin citadels a reality
uh but it means nothing but giving
people a chance to find ways to live
together with other people that
more are more conforming to their norms
and
have a more open approach to innovation
in trying out new ways new technologies
new norms and figuring out what works
and learning from your mistakes and
that's really the biggest problem
uh austrian school economists have with
politics that it's a field where people
don't have to learn and usually have
other people pay for their own mistakes
and that's the main difference i'd say
between politics and catalactics
i have a question also in terms of
epistemology
and there is so
mises in the subjective theory of value
out of this hayek brings the pretense of
knowledge right that centralized
planning
uh and it can or quantitative analysis
of the economy
does not make sense um but now
some pseudo-economists are saying that
because
bitcoin's 21 million supply cap
is quote-unquote the first constant of
human action
that this changes hayek's uh assessment
of the pretense of knowledge
and more specifically that because we
now have this economic constant
that we can for example predict the
exchange rate of bitcoin to other
assets uh and i'm curious what you think
of it yeah
no we can predict the relative
importance
of bitcoin at the 21 million it's an
arbitrary number
it's a it's a nice number i think it's
not arbitrary that there's a cap
and really the one of the major
innovations of bitcoin is that
kind of digital scarcity has been
possible to create
so that is groundbreaking i think but
it's not about the objective number
that's not important
the important is it's a technological
breakthrough not because it's very
innovative it's an innovative
combination of technologies that were
here and they solved a kind of economic
problem
but it's not even clear right now what
problem it is is a very complex problem
it arises due to the nature of human
exchange and between people who don't
trust each other or can't trust each
other fully because they don't know each
other
and uh there's always this
misunderstanding that there's something
objective
in numbers but in economics it's really
about the subjective relevance
of it it's not scarcity in itself so
most people think well of course
something that scars is valuable that's
not true
something that's relatively scarce to
our valuation
is valuable a lot of scarce things which
have no value at all because we don't
care about them
uh it's really a relative scarcity
and of course no one could have
predicted with 100
certainty that it will be bitcoin uh
that gets this
valuation and growing valuation uh by
people
and you can't say well because it's kept
at 21 million you can cap anything you
can
create you can clone bitcoin infinitely
you can create new altcoins you can find
lower numbers
it doesn't matter i can create a new
coin tomorrow or within an hour
and cap it at a thousand and think i
have
even higher value there that would of
course be
an illusion so it's not about the
objective number but
technology is the part where we have
more objectivity so it's not the
analysis of means that's technology
what means can really work out and solve
our
ends but we have to bear in mind the
ends and the analysis of
ends is subjective is understanding
how and what people rank in their
preferences
that then leads to their decision making
when they really have to make a decision
there
uh and that happens at the margin so
asking yourself do you want to have
another
satoshi or do you want to have another
candy or
things like that where you have this
kind of trade off happening
and there's nothing objective that tells
you in advance
there are uh what that will be so you
can predict it
with hundred percent certainty of course
we are ourselves very contingent there's
a lot of biological physiological
and psychological things you can know
about human beings
and in a sense there's knowledge about
our nature so there's some objectivity
in it
but epistemologically it does not lend
you
the possibility to predict human
behavior because human behavior is not
only
individual behavior it's in a feedback
loop
of society and it comes from a mental
process so it's
already human beings are very complex as
an organism
there are a multitude of organisms we
are not just one organism we have plenty
of organisms that
live in synergy with us and our system
our body itself is very complex and
within this body something new emerge
the emergent order
which is in our brain and that's a new
layer of complexity it's not entirely
determined by our bio
biological body but of course it's
contingent our biological
body which means a lot of biological
influences there but it's a new layer of
complexity with emergent phenomena
and it's really the merchant complexity
that's only recently been understood in
the natural sciences which is at the
core
of the epistemology of the austrian
school
and it's not only that this layer would
be enough
which is already like a stacked layer on
the complexity of our body
stacked on the complexity of life
stacked on the complexity of evolution
sticked on the complexity of the
universe
and then stacked onto that complexity of
our mental layer
we have the cultural layer of people
exchanging learning from each other
imitating each other
and once you have these kind of feedback
loops and processes you know as a
natural scientist okay that's a new
order of complexity emerging there
so you can't predict uh from the
biological layer
entirely what will happen on in the
social order uh so there's no link you
can make with
uh to the 21 million and somehow say
that's
objective uh because it's in our nature
to value something that is limited to 21
million as opposed to 25 million or 30
million
that's really not relevant what's
relevant is the technological solution
and we're still figuring trying to
figure out why
it's a means to people most people still
think it's
it's or don't get it or don't
understand it
and usually this lack of understanding
is a lack of empathy
lack of trying to figure out why people
see it as a means to what kind of
problems
and uh it's amazing that i mean uh we
have
20 21 and has still so many people in
particular academic economies out there
server has broken down what was that
yeah we had to add just some technical
problems
just just continue
i should continue because most people
can hear me or
okay anyway i can stop here and open for
a question and and see if
most are still live thanks great great
answer
uh i agree so
so i have a question um have you
yeah you probably heard about the
properties of good money which
says uh what does it say
it says money has to be
scarce divisible momentum
yes and fine of course so
so so if that's an austrian at austrian
theory
what's what's your take on on this is it
is it useful
uh yes uh it's useful but in the context
it was proposed it was
proposed by carl menger as a way to
explain the historical emergence of a
medium of exchange
and really by uh the epistemological way
to understand it is to try to look
through the eyes of those people and try
to figure out what problems they had
and then you look at historical forms of
money and try to figure out why they
replaced
other forms of money um and why but
why there's a kind where there's a
repeating pattern of
certain goods uh triggering more
monetary demand or showing more monetary
demand
and of course then you end up with this
kind of characteristics
which seem objective because they're
about technology it's about
what kind of goods will be
better monetary technology which means
will be better means to serve the ends
of the people
and then you really have to understand
both of the ends of the people
and the clue about understanding is
there it gets really complex it's
understanding why some goods have a
marginal utility that's declining
less quickly than other goods you know
so this is a very complex complex
process
but it's easily understandable if you go
put yourself in the eyes
of a medieval ancient
trader and the problems he has
and you see still kind of these problems
if you see people exchange
cattle and have a monetary demand for
cattle
and you can compare it to meat for
example and there you see
that most goods if you bring them to the
market in larger quantities
the marginal utility decrease is too
much
so that's a challenge for exchange among
people who don't know each other so you
have a foreign foreigner coming to your
village
and he tries to exchange with you and he
brings
something if he brings a good
he supplies it onto the market and maybe
the forced unit
still has a very high marginal utility
but the fifth sixth tenth unit will tend
to have a much lower marginal
utility because there's only a limited
number of exchange partners that
he'll find because they really have a
strong need for that good
and then it's the opposite order of
preferences that's how you call it so
it's really a very rare matching there
and so this kind of subjective
objectivist methodology from the bottom
up helps us to understand technologies
and technology of course in a very
general term
technology can be using cattle instead
of meat
even though it seems less practical
because everyone knows how to eat meat
but not everyone knows how to handle
cattle
uh it's more complicated it's a capital
good why
why is there a tendency to use cattle
instead of meat as a medium of exchange
and the reason of course some
characteristics and they also explain
why
cattle is abandoned once our superior
monetary technology is found
which is even superior in those
characteristics and they still hold
fairly well that's amazing
it's written in the 19th century and it
still holds fairly well
as a description and even a predictive
kind of help in figuring out what kind
of monetary technologies
will get larger adaptions and which
won't
uh what one addition here i actually
believe that this listing of the
qualities of money go much further back
i think it was either
aristotle or socrates who put out this
list
so this is many many decades before
austrian economists come to play
where carl menger makes a crucial
innovation here is that
he's he says that it does not really
matter the durability and such
what what is the the fundamental reason
or the definition of money is
the most saleable good and that's that
liquidity aspect with a very slowly
decreasing marginal diminishing return
as was said earlier so yeah it's it's
actually not
austrian per se there's this fungibility
divisibility what's austrian is the
saleability of money
yes yes uh in a way that's what i tried
to say that there's not too much
agreement only i would say the least
of the characteristics it was not only
the austrians but in that context advice
that in that context
that's peculiarly austrian of course you
had i mean those are fairly simple
attributes so you had them before
rarely in a comprehensive list so in a
comprehensive list
it's some other modern economists are
fairly close
but manga also provides this i would say
more or less complete list and then in
the engines you have aristotle
figuring out some parts you have even
plato figuring out other parts uh
play-doh is good about scarcity i think
is there
already and the defunct ability i think
is very slow
but as a comprehensive list yeah but
you're absolutely right the crucial
thing is the
less quickly falling of the marginal
utility and the term for it is
saleability or
upsatin german so sailability or
marketability
you could call it and that's a specific
characteristic
but it's not an objective characteristic
it's not something that you can measure
that you can find
it's a concept which i think has proved
to be very useful it's a very important
concept so
total agreement here
so i'm using it as a specification
because i'm a developer
and i need a specification for
writing good money which is bitcoin
and then if you think about it that way
you can make a
whole bunch of useful things about all
kinds of bitcoin projects
you could even figure out which one is
relevant which one
someone should be working on based on
this
specification yeah i mean it's a
starting point
um i i think it gets more complicated
than that because you have to figure out
if the ends are still similar and
comparable
to historical situations where this list
has proved to be comprehensive
and we can't be sure about that
and i think a crucial other insight
which goes back to hayek is that money
maybe
has been misunderstood as a noun but
it's not really the question if
something is money or not money
it's a more dynamic uh process
where you have increased moneyness of
some goods
and less moneyness of something else and
of course that's the concept of
saleability
you could translate it as moneyness
and that shows itself of course you can
define something as money and say it's
of supreme sellability
but there's no economic law that tells
you
uh what it's going to look like because
sellability is more of a bottom-up
emergent phenomenon it's not an
objective characteristics it's
really finding other people who are
still uh
taking it up in larger and larger
quantities
and i think there's still a lot to be
understood about
bitcoin uh adoption that's why even most
economies of the ocean school
didn't get it and still are fairly
skeptical i
uh i think i was the first one to be
sympathetic
towards bitcoin but it was because i
tried to be humble
not to exclude from what we've seen in
history
and extra extrapolate but try to really
understand uh the ends and one of the
most important end in the beginning was
avoiding capital controls of china so
there was one of the earliest use cases
for bitcoin
and of course there's some universality
in history that appears
but it tended not to be that important
and not that principally important
and another thing of course uh is the
new
monetary order which has led to a
monetization of a lot of different
assets
so i think generally it's misleading i
would say it's misleading to look at
things and ask yourself are they money
or not
and do they fulfill this list of
characteristics uh
no i think the list of characteristics
is useful in figuring out
can they have a higher moneyness could
it be a superior monetary technology
than the alternatives but
the problem of money has become much
more complex because
due to the impossibility to have long
term
too long between the long term preserve
the purchasing power
of the usual medium of exchange most
the people with who have lots of money
have been pushed
into a wide range of assets and are
pushed in more and more assets you have
so you have a monetization of a lot of
exotic assets
and of course you can ask yourself is it
painting
money or not and of course obviously it
has a lot of monetary demands if lots of
paintings
end up in uh
in warehouses in geneva at the airport
and no one looks at them anymore
so of course it's kind of the artistic
uh
value in the demand for the artistic
value relative
compared to the monetary value of it
being a financial asset disappears
uh instead you'll have a hard time
understanding that
just going from the characteristics of
what is money and what ain't money
so i think uh bitcoin can better be
understood in the context
of people looking for alternative assets
not
generally not only solving an exchange
problem here not only solving a currency
problem here
but solving other problems that as well
and at the same time and maybe even more
importantly
uh because otherwise you'd have uh
usually
people then would uh disagree to bitcoin
being money or having moneyness and
they'd say oh it's only used for illegal
stuff
oh it's only used to avoid cable
controls oh it's only used as a means of
speculation
and i think it's a lot of different ends
overlapping and many of those ends are
not really organic organic ends they are
an
artifact of the surrounding financial
and monetary order
but still they are there and need to be
understood
and i i think it lends to a more solid
understanding of how bitcoin can be a
means
for the ends of the people adopting it
and using it and demanding it
in without showing uh decreasing
marginal utility
and you see with those people who are
into bitcoin and not everyone
will be on on this call or in this meet
up
uh they tend to show the same pattern of
holding of staking and that means uh
no decrease no obvious decrease in
marginal utility uh
as there's never enough uh uh
uh is never the case if someone who
demands bitcoin uh you're asking why you
already have one why do you want more
and how much do you want it's this
typical
monetary phenomenon of
almost no decrease in marginal utility
which means you take more and more
of something that has a higher moneyness
you want more and more and more
and you see the same thing in other
financial assets
and again sealability is subjective
right so bitcoin
is very moneyness for some people and
not yumminess
for others exactly
but of course there's a kind of
objective layer in the sense uh
even as austrian economist we have to
look at history and even if it's a very
short-term history it's a 10-year
history now
uh or a bit more even than that and
we can look at patterns and uh
i i think uh one part or
one kind where it becomes ideology is
not wanting to look at the pattern it's
and a lot of people look at bitcoin and
look at it as if it has
newly emerged something very new with no
history behind it
and does they analyze it as if it was
or 2011 but there's a history behind it
and this history forces us
to be more empathetic and trying to
figure out
why does it mean the things it means to
the people who've adopted it
because there's an economic reality to
it and that's the
objectivity of the catalytic order once
a lot of people show a demand for
goods it becomes relevant on the market
we see that as market phenomena
so catalytic seems a bit more objective
not in the sense that we can predict but
in the sense that we see patterns and
the patterns are relevant it's not
entirely subjective it's not something
you can ignore
you can say okay it's something i'm not
interested in because it can become
relevant to you because
you are part of an extended exchange
order so you have to care
about what other people value and the
relative valuations
and that's why there is a problem of
calculation
and that's why there is uh there are
people trying to plan that
people trying to anticipate and it gets
a kind of rationality the market order
kind of market discipline where you need
to care
about the values of other people to a
larger extent
than if it was just their food choices
their subjective preferences it gets a
kind of objectivity
in the relative price structure of the
market around you
so bitcoin is not at the stage anymore
where you can ignore it so we can say
okay
some crazy people have that crazy hobby
and that
crazy spleen and they collect that crazy
stuff
i think it has reached the point where
anyone who
is part of markets can't ignore it as a
phenomenon if he likes it or not that's
not relevant
if you dislike it or not anyway you need
to
understand it and you need to bear in
mind that
it reflects the behavior of human agents
who are relevant for you
or who may become relevant for you
and i've seen with some members of the
austrian school that they tend to be too
ideological i think and
in the sense they don't want to look at
history
because they know it already or seem to
know
it already from theory and i don't i
think that's a
wrong approach as well i think we need
to look at what's happening we need to
look at history
not for epistemological reasons but to
challenge ourselves and to figure out if
the concepts are working are correct
if we're still understanding the world
or rationalizing something legitimizing
something
yeah patrick just speak up yeah hello
can you hear me
yes great um i have a question do you
think
uh there are some issues with the
austrian school as well
so do you think there are some theories
or some areas where other schools of
thought
have more to add or have a better view
of reality than the austrian school or
do you think it's all
all of the other theory in period sure
if you understand the austrian school as
a niche
tradition within the subdiscipline of
economics
then yeah i wouldn't recommend it
there's not that much value
in it so i wouldn't even recommend to
study austrian economics at university
or something like that
because that's a general
misunderstanding
it's a tradition in another sense i
think it's a tradition that goes
back to a trend and
that was important in the 19th century
in vienna and this kind of austrian
enlightenment i would call it
and it picked up a lot of the thought of
the scottish enlightenment
because it was so similar in its
dynamics because a lot of these major
insights were already
in the scottish enlightenment there but
it became more profound and more modern
of course
in in the austrian school um and so is
this this kind of tradition which is uh
inter
trying in an interdisciplinary way to
understand social phenomena
in their whole complexity and being
aware that's it's a
one of the highest layers of
complexities of complexity
that there are for human understanding
okay
that's one of the major parts of this
tradition
um uh on of course that's not just
economics and that's something that
changes over time and that's something
that learns from new disciplines and new
insights
and i don't think you can be a good
economist and i'm reiterating
hayek i think that's an important
insight you can't be a good economist if
you're only an economist so if you meet
someone who is an austrian economist and
he's only an economist
and he even tells you i'm not interested
in history i'm not interested in
technology i
um then i wouldn't take him very
seriously
uh because uh it doesn't work that way
you can't just from economic theory
which is just the sub
branch let's say the catalytics of
practiology
you can't understand everything because
you don't know how to weigh the concepts
you don't know what's really important
uh at the present uh and so on
so i have a very different understanding
i think it's the original
understanding of the austrian school but
it was always
uh it always had problems
so already in the second generation of
the austrian school there's always this
need from the surrounding society to
apply
something so many became politicians
and of course you have all these kind of
distortions how do you apply
on open-ended theory to the world
if the causal structures are so complex
if there's always a time
gap between the cause and the results
and the understanding of the results
so that's almost impossible to uh
withdraw in insights from a theory
that then you can apply immediately and
be completely sure and the sure you are
about it the more it's assigned in your
own
uh or you see something that's not
relevant
so i'm very open to every discipline but
i'm also i try to measure them using
their own standards
and i think if you apply the methods of
mainstream economics to mainstream
economics
you need to you'll figure out that it's
a bluff it's a great bluff
uh and it's not because the people are
stupid
it's not because they're evil it's
because of
the incentives as they are it's because
of
the general governmental structures
uh that we live in it's about the
general institutional structures about
the question who is an academic
uh where do his crit do his credentials
come from what's the
end that credentials are meant to
fulfill
uh how did it develop how did it change
what's the need for economists
particularly economists
and so on and if you apply the same
scrutiny to disciplines i
i i think you uh tend to get a very
critical
approach to what most of modern
social sciences and
uh the way policy is
deduced from uh
seemingly scientific traditions uh
so i i tend to think that the austrian
school is a different tradition
can be a different tradition uh one of
my
teachers was the most important student
of hayek who was an entrepreneur a
german entrepreneur
olan bada and my other teacher was hans
hermann hopper the student of rothbard
who was a philosopher
maybe so this was one side was very
theoretical but interdisciplinary
rooted in other traditions and the other
was a very practical
approach i'd say and very down to earth
in in the experience of an entrepreneur
which is very different from the
experience of a politician or an
academic
so i i don't think it's a mono causal
or it can be misunderstood and as i said
in the beginning
mostly it's misunderstood as an ideology
but that's not bad that's the way we
work
most people are interested in ideas
because they're looking for
rationalizations for
they want we want to look ourselves in
the mirror we want to find reasons why
what we
want uh is good for us and for everyone
else
and that's the main demand for theory
comes from there
we selectively look for things that
confirm
our prior perceptions and our interests
and and that's the way it is so it's
nothing bad about that that's that's how
it is and
the austrian school becoming more
ideological in the united states was a
great thing for the tradition because it
in the context it co it gave it a little
bit of a
protective layer from academia which
tended to become quite pragmatic
in this game of expertise for political
reasons
so the austrian school was left a little
bit outside of academia and
prestigious academics wouldn't touch it
and that's protected i think some
crucial parts of it
some i think are still very important
in it and it's a kind of contrarianism
it's a kind of
general skeptical outlook towards
institutions
and the willingness to measure our
with or hold them to their own measures
and not just
uncritically accept the status quo as it
is
so i i think that it was a good turn it
protected it
but i think the real value of it is in
this open ended
and never ending effort to understand
social phenomena but it's a very niche
interest so
and i know and that's the way it is that
most people don't really care that much
about it because it seems too
theoretical
it seems hard to apply why would you
discuss epistemology
which is really so abstract and so
generalized
that most people wouldn't figure out
what's why it's important and why why
there's a need for it
and that's fine so for most people
austrian economics is a way to
rationalize things they have failed and
experienced
and usually it's not the worst people i
think really good people
seeing austrian economics something that
appeals to
intuitions and i
i think uh it's a symptom
of some positive things that more people
get
interested in austrian economics it'll
always
remain a niche field but nowadays more
people come
from bitcoin to austrian economics than
from austrian economics to bitcoin and
that itself is a symptom of
of change that's happening and part of
that is very positive
as people having a more open-minded
approach to institutions
and to innovation in institutional
or in innovative alternatives to
institutions that have outlived the
usefulness
to us and are showing the problems
every day and every day becoming more
obvious
that the institutions we've come
to accept as with being without
alternative
are under tremendous pressure uh to cope
with that increased complexity of
interconnected global order
with the technologies that we use now
and with
digital interconnectedness that we have
nowadays
and it's a very interesting time to be
alive and i think
tradition uh like the austrian school in
this original things will prove very
useful to those
few people who have the patience and
open-mindedness to
embark on that journey because the
journey without obvious usefulness in in
the beginning
you can predict how it will be useful to
you in the long
term
and maybe one thing to add here is that
praxeology is about the
causal consequences of actions right so
it explains what happens when you act it
does not explain
why people act or why they value the
things that they do
so these are question of philosophy
sorry of psychology
not of praxiology but interestingly here
uh
freud and jung were both in vienna at
the same time
were the other austrians were thinking
about economics and they were even
partaking in the midtown style
so i would say that union psychology
is very much in line with praxeology
even though it asks very different
questions
yeah the interesting thing is that when
jung wrote about economics
and politics it was obviously
he was obviously very close to the
austrian school of economics
which is really surprising to read that
uh
now uh i i don't think that austrian
economics means you're not interested in
psychology it was what mises proposed is
a clear cut an epistemological content
he called
yes the question of asking why people
like the way the ethymology
because he also didn't like the term
psychology and i think he was right i
mean psychology also has his own
problems and has become a discipline
uh and has cyclical fashions uh
and tends to have in particular in the
post and the freudians they're not freud
himself but the fraudians
are quite simplistic understanding of
human beings
but generally i think as an austrian
economist you need to have a strong
interest
in that psychological layer it's just
that you know
that the logic of human action is on the
mental layer it doesn't come from
it's not entirely determined by the
biological and evolutionary mechanisms
before because it's a new layer
and the social interaction layer is a
new layer there
which always means a new layer of
complexity means you don't
in the methods you need to have another
method you can predict the
outcome from a lower layer of complexity
uh reaching there
otherwise it would be a very simplistic
materialistic
outlook on human behavior and it's just
wrong it
just doesn't have a predictive power uh
and it misses
what's most essential about the human
beings
um yeah but i i think it's it's crucial
and interesting to
to look at this kind of timology
entomology it comes from the
understanding moods more or less
but that would be another x course quite
complicated
what that field really in its essence
boils
down to mises thought it's a kind of
history of moods and and
history of mental states so like a
history of mental states of human beings
and
uh and junk uh
looked at it as the history even of
mental states and time of archetypes and
dream patterns and so on so that was
very much how
mises perceived that field of research
to be so i agree with you and it's very
interesting that this
that there's not only one austrian
school there's so many viennese schools
which also there's an
intellect development and an
interconnected development here
uh of research and of coping
uh with the problems of modern society
that's why i'd rather call it an
austrian enlightenment and i think this
tradition is part of that austrian
enlightenment
which is in the tradition of the
scottish enlightenment
which is also an eternal tradition
where you have a lot of ancient
predecessors
this kind of interdisciplinary
open-minded critical
socratic approach to understanding
social phenomena
which bridges theory and practice
it's not just utopian it's not just
idealized it's not just
nominalistic it's some it's realistic
it's a realist tradition
i saw that lucas had a question earlier
so what's up
hi now i just wanted to make a i wanted
to make a comment about the
the adam's question about the properties
of money and what i wanted to say is
that
to me the the idea of that
there are some intrinsic properties that
make money money
or or some kind of money makes no sense
because
i think it is basically what we have to
do is basically apply the same
subjective value
theory to money and basically
that that's all because if i for example
i i'm sure in europe it's not doesn't
work in this way but for example here if
you want to pay me
to buy me my car and pay me with euros
or i will accept the ratio or
or dollars why not i know that they are
not
counterfeited so i i trust you so i will
accept it and i could accept many other
things too
so and in fact
i i
i know because there was
things here were messy years ago and
people accepted many different things
many many many different things that
uh as money sometimes with some
discount depending on of the quality
let's say
or the acceptability of the of the
thing that you offer us money
but yes in the end it's basically there
is a
rate between different things and you
accept one or
or not and it's so what we call money is
just because
it's so acceptable it's but it's not
because
it possessed any specific property
at all uh yeah i'm somewhere in between
so i would agree with you that it's
overrated that's what i
tried to answer before i would not agree
that makes no sense
because i said it made sense in the
context of understanding the historical
emergence
of the higher moneyness of certain goods
so there it made absolute sense
the characteristics and they really
helped explain
now they may make some sense in the for
the technological questions now about
the means
but that makes no sense if you only look
at the means without looking at the end
so there i would agree with you
uh the more important thing is
understanding the ends
and how the means are related to the
ends and then you can't answer from the
list of characteristics and that's why i
meant before
uh i don't think you can understand
bitcoin or any other monetary phenomena
just by going to this list
that was meant to describe the
historical process of the emergence of
certain goods
of money so um yeah i i think i'm
somewhere in between
and i'm reluctant to have this kind of
zero and one answers
to stuff it doesn't mean i'm relativist
i think the
money as itself is such a complex
concept that is a lot of different
aspects in there and it's hard to tell
which one
are the most important ones of course if
you just look at
the need to exchange with foreigners
there's a lot of network effects the
markets always have network effects
and a lot of this kind of infrastructure
which is
technology as well so you can have a
market infrastructure
is network effects it means
why is the trading place at the place
it's it usually because it's the
confluence of roads or or rivers
we don't know if it's the perfect
location it's just a location where
most traders ended up and the more
traders they are the more traders come
there of course and the larger
the fare becomes so that's network
effects
so it's not never always objective if
you have interaction there's always this
kind of reflectiveness
in our behaviors we look at what other
people are doing and we change our
pattern accordingly so that would be
very misleading
and that's of course is behind a lot of
fallacies in economics to look at
objective things
and uh forget that
we really need to put ourselves through
the eyes or look through the eyes of the
economic agents the decision makers and
that subjectivism
and that's really about figuring out
what were the
ends and why was the means for that end
it may turn out that in certain
situations
uh the biggest problem was the network
and in other situations the biggest
problem was durability and in another
situation
the biggest problem was fungibility
but it could be other things other
aspects which
menger could not see because he looked
at the historical
processes maybe a new order
of course once we pass more and more of
our lives in in virtual
worlds and digitalized worlds it may be
a very different technological uh
characteristics that are export
important for that kind
of exchange networks effect effects to
arise
so i think that proof is somewhere in
between
i don't think you can look at the
characteristics they're not an economic
law they're describing
characteristics of a technology in a
particular context
related to particular ends of people but
when you understand those ends you
realize
that a lot of them are universal and a
lot of them are timeless
so that's why it makes sense to look at
history and to look at the old theory
from the 19th century and you can still
learn something
about the presence and even the future
maybe and i think there's already so
much in manga
that is much more than even contemporary
monetary economics from the mainstream
uh
they haven't provided more insights but
rather more fallacies
so overall i think it's better to read
manga now than a modern monetary
economist usually i'm i don't mean to
ridicule
that but i think in the end it's about
understanding these means and relation
of human beings and then of course you
have to apply it to the particular
context
and go deep into the real history of the
real people
exchanging assets uh taking part in
exchange
and figuring out what it was that they
saw in that and are still seeing in that
so we are bitcoin developers we are
literally changing the way of bitcoin is
working right
but in order for us to modify bitcoin we
have to
like know what is the right direction to
modify bitcoin too
right and in order for
for that we have to ask the question
what's the best money we might be able
to conceptualize
and then work towards it and and
and do you have any better framework for
for answering that question than the
properties of good money
yeah uh i i think it has been
underestimated by most people
uh and that's one of the inside
now make a difference between those have
adopted bitcoin and see it as a superior
money
it's really the question of hoarding and
the importance of hoarding
and the austrian school is value neutral
about hoarding
uh and does be more friendly so we see
uh the action of hoarding of holding on
to
an asset without direct news for
yourself and without knowing what you
will use it for
later on it seems a bit irrational to
many academics
we see it as a means that people
use for legitimate ends they have and
the end is to cope with our senescence
with the fact that we are growing older
and our capacity to earn income
decreases
uh with our lifetime that means in our
nature there's something that tends and
tries to hold on to
the produce from our work
in order to cope with the uncertainty of
the future
and i i think that's the main
aspect of bitcoin and i didn't know it
from the beginning
when i first looked at bitcoin i thought
it's an exchange system for like-minded
people
and that was a very common
misunderstanding so i looked at bitcoin
in the sense does it have the
technological property
to be an easy to use exchange system
uh for people who always share the same
values because they are libertarians
they are geeks maybe uh and i looked at
that then i was a bit skeptical i i was
sympathetic
i stumbled upon bitcoin very very early
so i wasn't negative but i was skeptical
i thought now it's
that won't get that kind of moneyness
where you have a medium of exchange and
that
generally accepted i didn't see that as
very likely
and what i've tried to come to term with
in understanding this
this adoption and going through many
cycles
since then was apparently
uh my interpretation now
is that the thing
giving bitcoin value as
as a lower limit of valuation is what i
would call
artistic collection so there's social
collection where you want to collect
stuff to show off
to increase your status but there's a
kind of artistic collection
where we tend to hold on to things
because we like the idea of having more
of it
and i think initially bitcoin was that
experiment where more and more people
thought it's fun it feels good to hold
on to those coins
we don't know if it's gonna be money and
no one in 2010 11
thought it is or very few people thought
it's very likely that one day a
sovereign nation will
have a legal tender law with bitcoin and
so on it was seemed to be a geeky
thought to be a geek experiment but i
think what emerged
uh was this kind of self-reinforced
uh collecting of bitcoins which is a
kind of it's a non-monetary demand and
it was one of mises insights it's really
hard to explain monetary demand just by
monetary demand because you go in
circles
and then it's just you demand what
everyone else is demanding because he
expects
everyone else to demand it
and i think bitcoin is different in the
sense that it
seems to have a more and more stable
layer of collectible demand
and it would be great if the exchange
layer would really work and i'm
pretty optimistic about lightning and so
on
uh but i had to come to terms like most
people that we've seen
increasing bitcoin adoption with no
sign of increasing bitcoin exchange in
the sense of used for monetary
transactions day-to-day transactions
and i mean still most people don't
really get it and it looks very much
like a speculative
thing that you hold on to uh
but i'm still optimistic long term that
it could be the sweet spot between
something that has a
base layer of collectible demand and
have
monetary qualities and get the network
effect
unnecessary so
you see it's a very complicated
differential way of trying to explain
what has happened so far and trying then
to predict
with it i don't think if you would have
asked an economist even if you had asked
myself
in 2010 that i would have been able to
give a lot of guidance
i think it was 2012 that i first
recommended someone to
buy bitcoin because i thought i figured
out if there's an upside in monetary
demand it's going to be huge
and the downside is just your investment
so if you buy a 400 euro bitcoin the
upside will be huge
and they proved to be a correct insight
but
as for the technological details a lot
of it
i think is in the resilience of this
trustless structure
and that's something we learn every day
we don't know what news will happen
tomorrow i mean
we don't know what the chinese are after
the only thing we know is that for more
than 10 years
it has proven to be resilient
and it has proven to be more resilient
that most
reasonable people thought possible uh
so i think there's a kind of of course
that's a historical
explanation but the same holds true for
precious metals is not
something objective from economic
theories nothing such as intrinsic value
that's usually
uh that's a fallacy that you think
something has intrinsic value because
it's physical
or because cost has gone into it because
it was so expensive to mine uh
that those are fallacies uh even
sometimes uh people following the
austrian school make those
mistakes but they are very uh basic
mistakes that's the cost theory
of value and that's wrong uh so it's all
the subjective theory of value you
really is about understanding the ends
of people and figuring out
if it can be a means in the long term
now people can see
something subjectively as a means and
that becomes problematic and carl menger
already wrote about that
now you have to look at the
technological side but that of course is
uncertain because you don't know if you
figure out the technology and figure out
if what people expect from it as a means
can hold true if there's
technological possibility that it works
out
uh people just through their uh thinking
can make something work or seemingly
work we see it in medicine and
menger gave the example of medicine he
says you can make a physiological
analysis
chemical analysis of something and
realize it's a placebo
still it may be working because the
mental
understanding is so crucial for it but
the interest in the technological and
physical side of it can help you predict
a little bit you'd say okay
if uh medication only works because it's
a placebo maybe it won't be that
sustainable in the long run
and it may be replaced by more effective
technologies in the long run because
people in the long run prefer
health to death and life like health to
sickness and life to death
that was the least valuation that that
mises proposed as a kind of minimum
valuation which we assume
not as absolutely true but something
very plausible
so there's no way to predict from
economic theory if the technological
promise of bitcoin will hold
but as a good economist you have to look
at the reality and say well there's a
reality of more than a decade of it
holding the promise
and uh not because the the most
intelligent people predicted it
to hold it's uh because somehow it was
the sweet spot between the ends people
had in the time that they were living in
in the
means provided by this technology and
of course technology is much more than
than just the
distributed ledger technology and so on
every kind of
network effect is a kind of social
technology of
people buying into something so
uh i i i don't think uh
the approach is right to to or or i
think what good
theory helps you is to be more humble in
your approach more entrepreneurial
and not thinking that you're not
thinking that you're too clever
so that you can design the perfect money
because then you always see the faults
with everything that's there
nothing is perfect in this world uh
because a lot of
like it's adopted because other people
adopted it so
i think it's a little different to think
that bitcoin is the most
perfect money there ever was and ever
will be
that's too much this puts much too much
into it
because it was not created by god it's a
product of human beings it's adopted by
human beings
it may turn out to be one of the best or
the best solutions for
certain kinds of problems people have in
the modern world
and a lot of those problems are eternal
and timeless problems
that's by i'm positive about bitcoin and
i tend to agree with the approach that's
a bit more conservative
in trying to have full backward
compatibility in trying to be
more humble and very careful in trying
to improve
uh what is working so don't fix what
it's not broken
i think there if you want to take no
technological
uh prediction or or help from theory
it really it tells the engineer don't
buy into someone from the social
sciences thinking
that he can approach society like an
engineer that's not how it works as an
engineer you know about the messiness
of solutions and you know about
trade-offs
and you'll be extra careful
uh with those kind of assets the longer
they are in place the longer the track
record
behind it and but still i mean where i
would
disagree with a very maximalist
proposition is i think there's still
uh i i would suggest to anyone who
thinks he has a better idea or sees
characteristics that would improve
upon it to experiment on its
but see it as a trial and error kind of
way and only
in a kind of voluntary proposal
uh and i dislike that the whole
financial field of course is full of
scams and scheme like uh
let's say imprecision and marketing
uh and so on so i tend to be more
down to earth and and i have more the
approach of someone from the natural
sciences or an engineer
who would take a more careful approach
in trying to fix or improve up on
something
but innovation is crucial and innovation
is possible if there's competition
and competition means the skin in the
game so that those people who think that
something
uh can work better should put the money
where their mouth is
and then let's figure out and it's not
that we started new
we already have a track record we can
already learn from the past
and we can try to
bear that in mind with every decision we
make
yeah good point
okay i would have another question if
nobody else has one
but i don't want to mock the
conversation
okay me can i sure no
no my idea about the
the the idea that
there are properties that make
one money better than other is that if
those properties really exist and are
um just like that then
by maximizing those uh properties
you are maximizing the quality of the
money
right yes and i i don't think that is
that is because it is like a flower
right there are no a flower that is
better than other
it's just you want a flower
for a girl and it depends what the girl
yeah what flower the girl prefer
is the one that is more valuable by you
because
you want the flower right so for example
if well we tend to believe that i'm more
um there is a
i don't think so the the the best
property is what
the girl that you love
prefer basically that you are going to
pay more for
that one so basically if you
um we used to think that
uh fungibility or industry which
or make beacon in this team which will
sorry i don't know the word you know one
equal to other
yes or it's better but some people
don't like that there are people who
prefers
very very well or very easy to trace
bitcoins for example and they are going
to
pay more for that kind of bitcoins
than for those that are mixed or
anonymized
for example so that's what i wanted to
say
the the the better bitcoin is the the
one that
the people prefers
right how the other value of the bitcoin
is
it's not that you just can't maximize
the
the the properties yeah that's again i i
i partly agree with you and i probably
disagree i i think it's a very important
point to make as one part of a spectrum
and there's the other spectrum
uh the other part of the spectrum is
thought is those that insist that
there's something objective
uh and that's a fallacy but i think it's
a fallacy as well to think that
subjectivism does not mean that
everything is subjective
because in catalectics as it's about the
exchange of foreigners
there are patterns and we see patterns
emerging it's not
uh i mean if you go uh
to pick up a girl yeah let's say um
not in a demeaning sense of course you
can say oh it doesn't matter and
whatever she likes and makes her happy
will work out but of course there's a
sense that it makes sense to have a
general interest in the patterns of
human interaction
and then of course that may uh shrink a
bit
the range of options that you're looking
at yeah
there's a less likeliness of certain
kinds of flowers to be attractive and
the
greater liking list of other kinds of
flowers and
in particular in exchange between
foreigners where there's not so much
where we are we disagree we need to find
the common ground
and this common ground usually there
must be something more
universal that's why it's a very it's a
minimum
interface that you're looking for for
this exchange and there are much clearer
patterns
so the austrian school is a bit between
the heterodox schools of economics and
the orthodox one the orthodox is overly
objectifying it's like there are rules
and models and they are true
and they tell you from the
characteristics what you've got to
expect
that's yeah but the heterodox
get to go too far
they think that it's all relative and so
it's just the interests
and there is no real uh patents there
other than the patents you decide to
have so
society just agrees on the kind of
economic order it wants to have
and that's a kind of utopian thinking
because of course there's a kind of
pattern in human behavior
and we see that in monetary phenomena
it's not that everything emerges it's
not
that there's there's a diversity but
it's not an endless diversity the
surprising thing is that we got
get the emergence of very similar forms
in very different cultures and you need
to explain that you can't just say well
it's
chance yeah because if you have a
pattern like that
so it's somewhere in between i'd say i
think your point is very important
because most people tend to
air i mean now under the impression of
course of orthodox economics as well so
maybe your point is even more important
they tend to err in the direction of
objectivity
but you can also air in the direction of
relativism i don't
think that there's nothing you can say
from theory theory helps you a bit to
understand the pattern
and um and i i think there's more we can
say about money than just it's just the
thing that people prefer to accept
because we see a much smaller diversity
of what works
in those functions and shows sustainable
monetary demand
uh where's the diversity of tastes uh
and so on and even on the market we see
that it's not an endless diversity it's
a huge diversity of goods if you have
competition
but there are obvious patterns of
scaling is very important you have
economies of scale
uh and and they are not the same in
every kind of product
so there is this size seemingly regular
patterns there which
people who do catalectics which is this
part of praxeology
where they tend to find some agreement
with orthodox economies so going back to
the question
why does it seem like milton friedman in
some fields
tends to say the same thing as austrian
economists is because he's just looking
at the most obvious patterns that we
know even
if you are a socialist or not it doesn't
matter
the rationing of some things price
controls will have an
impact not deterministic
but as a pattern that you can observe
again and again
and you see very similar processes uh
in the behavior of goods and people uh
about goods in
socialist economies and market
economists
uh and that's a sign that there are
patents that go back to the
nature of human beings and the logic of
human action
so i i don't think that we can say
nothing and we can't explain at all why
bitcoin
uh has been chosen to have the highest
uh
market capitalization of gold
cryptocurrencies
um we are challenged to explain that and
understand it and i don't
i don't think the the reason is that
it's the best technology and it's the
most perfect technology that doesn't
make sense to me
so it's not entirely in the objective
but it's not entirely subjective it's
not entirely by chance
you know so there's something else and
the large part can be network effects
but i'm pretty sure it's
it's not a hundred percent network
effects otherwise it would be just the
first one
that's there and no matter what and if
dogecoin was the first uh
cryptocurrency it would be now uh
dogecoin the most dominant currency i
don't think so
uh i think there's a bit more but i
think network effects play a huge part
uh in particular these kind of exchange
related
decisions and adoptions basically
patents and we're always challenged by
what's happening to explain
those things and theory helps a bit not
by adopting one
100 percent the old characteristics but
understanding where the character
characteristics come from and if those
ends are still may still be the same
today or what may have changed
so there may be additional
characteristics there may be trade-offs
that we don't see so i totally agree
just by looking at the list of
characteristics we see
in manga's writings that's not enough to
explain because there may be new
characteristics now
which is the most important trade-off
and so you optimize
all the known characteristics and you
optimize against the unknown
characteristics
characteristic which is more important
but you don't know it yet
and that's not the way carl menger came
to those
this list of characteristics he came in
a different way it's not
dogmatic he didn't propose it i've i i
say it that's it i look at
processes in history and try to figure
out what's the difference the objective
difference between different goods
if there's anything i can learn about
these patterns why do the same patterns
re-emerge
but between these two sites of which
your side is very uncrucially important
underrated maybe between these two sides
of
being too uh relativist and being too
cocksure
about the objectivity of our insights
and the data and effects and so on
somewhere in between that's good theory
i think
and by the way i think that one
characteristic missing out of this list
and that we realized that it was missing
in cyberspace is the verifiability
yes so that that people can verify that
the
transaction that they receive is valid
yeah and
and and that's what makes bitcoin so
amazing that
all transactions in the network were
valid and therefore you verify the total
money supply
yeah yeah i totally agree and i think if
a manga
would analyze that now he wouldn't start
with the list of characteristics
he would look at the phenomenon and i
think he
certainly would get it that trustless
verification is
one crucial characteristic here
so verifiability is don't mix it into
the supply verifiability
because that's scarcity right yeah yes
that's
that's not necessary
no actually i i don't it's
or
no i i i don't think that the very i
think the verifiability
for all transactions is is already
important
yeah but i think that's what he meant as
well it's uh it's two different aspects
yes yes yes it makes sense
um and maybe even another
other thing but this is really just my
speculation but there might be another
pattern that
that could possibly quantify in the
future to be a property of good money
which it would explain actually the rise
of ethereum
which is a programmability uh right
that doesn't also be something
yes but as always if you have various
characteristics there may be a trade-off
and
people will come to different
assessments
of this trade-off and i think i mean
that was one of the core
contention points in the block size wars
or debates
is what are the trade-offs if
more programming programmability
endangers the resilience
this kind of trustless verification i
don't know if it's
entirely that aspect but
i think it's not contentious to say now
there is there is disagreement and there
was strong disagreement about the kind
of trade-offs you'd have
between characteristics so it's not
clear that the best money
uh has a long list of good
characteristics is
it's about the right match the right
trade-offs between
characteristics and that's hard to
predict
yeah i mean it's and it's still not
entirely clear
if which side that was right i i tend
uh i tend to think that
that it's true that it's a trade-off
that is touring complete programmability
programmability increases the attack
vectors
i find that convincing as an argument it
doesn't tell me
if that means that in the sense of trade
off it's always worse
but it would tend to prefer uh
second layer solutions for
programmability
and not have it already in the first
layer
but those i think those are
technological questions that
theory can only tell you there well
there may be trade-offs so that's why i
think that may make sense to see
trade-offs here
and to be conscious of those trade-offs
[Music]
but i do agree that programmability is a
very interesting feature
and may turn out to be the crucial
feature
but then it's not that moneyness is just
one thing
i think it's a
once there's an infrastructure that
provides
services in this field i will realize
that
it can be a very differentiated
structure
and that's a monetary demand it's not
just one thing it's as a
because it doesn't disappear i mean uh
even if
uh uh the adoption of bitcoin increases
it doesn't disappear that there are
other assets and uh
so i think there'll always be other
financial assets obviously
and there'll always be a kind of
trade-off
in moneyness and different aspects where
you optimize
and i certainly think that uh
programmability
will tend to become more important i'm
not so sure
if it's a for the layer of looking for a
financial assets to protect purchasing
power
expect but pretty sure programmability
is important for additional layers
of uh financial infrastructure
and and maybe i'm not sure if
programmability is
is a good good enough word here because
our i think what the programmability
means is a
um a nuanced definition of property
rights
right and i and so here for example
right bitcoin single signature
the property right is defined as anyone
who can provide the signature of one key
can spend this coin and then for example
things like multi signatures like m
out of n of these keys into sign right
which then defines the property right of
that utxo
so maybe um uh what's it called
um constructability
no no no um there's like this word of
how
elaborate one can speak um
like one of the important realizations
is that that program ability
is in regards to property rights
definition
yeah i would obviously yeah that's an
important point it could be one
aspect not sure of it i i mentioned
before it's kind of touring complete
programmabilities already i know that
there are of course nuances in
programmability
and disagreement what what kind of
what's the import what's the essence of
programmability what do we need here is
it this kind of space for open-ended
experimentation
everything is possible or is it just
certain cases that we know in advance
which are more crucial than others and
in particular
multisig of course obviously seems to be
a quite important aspect of
programmability and then
the question i think it's different as
they may be related but that we don't
know for sure
yet is the differentiation of property
rights and transferability
uh of different aspects of property
rights
but then we can only figure out once
there's more innovation in the legal
sphere
that's why i think uh in order to get
the full potential of this kind of
digital revolution that may happen here
uh triggered from the bitcoin uh is we
need this kind of innovation and legal
structures as well and institutional
arrangements as well to really figure
out
uh the whole innovative potential here
of this technology
uh and i i tend to think that it'll be a
link of technological innovation and
legal innovations there
and that's why i'm so interested in this
free private cities field and
heading the foundation um i think you
need
their experimentations with the legal uh
uh
aspects and one i think crucial thing is
change from the the not innovative legal
cartels that we have usually is this
zero one
uh basically just state licenses you
either
own it uh or you don't own it
and everything else is done by
regulation whereas i think a much more
innovative solution is you have
various layers of property rights which
would be a much better solution to to
cope with externalities
and internalizing them
and yeah you can say composability of
property contract of course a lot of how
contractual arrangements can be done
but there is really a synergy between
legal innovations and technological
innovations so i don't think it's only
the
technological side that's why i'm a bit
skeptical it's only smart
contracts that solve everything i think
it's the match
of programmability or aspect of
programmability
and new legal arrangements that make
full use or best use of that
because there are always social
questions to be figured out
as well otherwise i mean you'd have the
smart contract but not the acceptance
not the execution
of it uh uh not obvious how you handle
conflict and so on
um so but i actually think this
this is one of the key innovations of
bitcoin in the legal realm
is that previously these property rights
laws basically
defined when it was justified to apply
force after the fact that something
happened
right so someone steals from you then
you can apply force to get the good back
um and what what bitcoin geniusly
manages
is that basically theft becomes
impossible
uh at you know at the like before the
act
it's just simply impossible to create a
signature without knowing the private
key
by then and so far it has not yet
happened that a coin a bitcoin was spent
without providing a valid signature
right so here that makes the property
rights definitions
not reliant on the retribution
retributional help of other people
which might be a definition of the
government um
and this is what i find so interesting i
called it non-simulated ownership
uh which is probably not the right term
but it's it's somewhat of a
yeah of a way to enforce property rights
solidly which was before not possible
yeah yeah i think you're on to something
uh definitely i
i think it's in in this field uh where
it's part part of the
frostlessness is that you have already a
lot of things that can only be provided
by institutions
outside done by technology
or on the technological side exactly
all right michael
or or anyone do you guys have questions
i i do have one more um
and basically that the definition
of a gold atom like the most
uh atomic unit of uh of the gold
monetary system
and that definition is not up to people
a gold atom has what 72
you know protons and that's just how it
is
and well contrarily the definition of
what is a satoshi
at the most atomic unit of the bitcoin
monetary sphere
is very much up to individuals and
seemingly to somewhat of a well
in in one sense it's up to the
individual full node
operator right who defines what software
he runs
and then verifies and enforces the other
people in the network
yet yet still for bitcoin to be useful
as we said earlier it does need to have
that
network effect and multiple people need
to agree on
the definition of what a satoshi is
now where i think this is the strongest
argument why gold is better than bitcoin
because the definition of the monetary
unit is
is not to the whim of individuals while
in bitcoin it seems to be where do you
think that that trade-off comes in
yeah i don't think that's true there's
always been
trying to explain in the physical as a
physicist
why gold has become so universally
but it wasn't that universal universally
used as money
and i i don't think that it's really
that physics can explain that of course
we know what are precious metals and we
know the importance
of gold but that's not the reason for
the gold adoption as it happened
because the fantastic metals out there
with fantastic properties
very interesting properties and
gold is a rather soft metal
with unique properties but i mean who
tells you that those properties should
be valued that way
and that an atom is the smallest unit
that's not obvious uh
a kalmenger had the concept of the
relevant unit he said it's not an
objective thing the relevant unit is
objective again it's asking
what can be the entity of your action
what can you act upon
if people think that they can act up on
a
gold atom which is possible what hasn't
really happened
i don't know anyone who talks about
actions of gold atoms
other than maybe someone in nanotech
so it's about a relevant unit and the
relevant unit has changed i mean
uh gold for a long time
there was a problem with the relative
scarcity to the demand of the people so
that the entities have a
very large purchasing power compared to
other goods
so gold wasn't the money of the regular
people usually it was silva
and the problem is even though gold can
be hammered out
to to infinitely thin layers
mechanically it wasn't quite possible
until fairly recently
so it was improvements innovations in
metallurgy
that led to gold uh being used
in in a more universal way making it
possible to replace
if we would still have used minting
which we didn't then using the
end uh to have replaced silver because
now it's possible to have basically a
gold foil you could include
integrate a gold foil into a paper uh
bill and still have the physical gold in
it
and that wasn't possible for most of the
time that gold was used
so i i don't think there's anything
physical about it there are some
objective criteria of gold which are
connected
to the social processes this led to its
adopt and
adoption in particular the religious
understanding that gold was the sun
metal and silver the moon metal
which gave a kind of credence to the
ratio of 1 to 12
which was the historically most
prevalent ratio of gold to pro
to silver relative prices was one to
twelve and that's exactly some to moon
uh cycles uh but it's just the
rationalization i think and then of
course there's you don't know what's
first
is it the idea or the behavior it's it's
interchangeable so it's about relative
unit
and there i don't see much of a
difference i think it's a
similar it's a similar phenomenon to
gold adoption
but gold adoption of course it's a bit
in the past
and we've seen a very early on
religious use of gold so it seemed to be
linked to status it seems to be linked
to something
uh interesting and relevant for people
and i think it's similar with bitcoin
for different reasons
uh it's nothing physical here it's what
people
perceived why did it make sense to want
more bitcoin i
uh i i used bitcoin when it was
basically free i i did some mining on my
laptop i
i i was around when there were the four
sets on the websites we got free bitcoin
and it was basically there was no way to
attach a price to it
and unfortunately i didn't hold on to
much of that and
i myself didn't of course as
almost everyone else i i didn't
associate anything of further price to
it
but some people over time held on to
more and more coins and thought it was
interesting to have more of them
rather than less because otherwise it
doesn't really you don't care
i mean it's an experiment it you don't
care if you have a hundred or a thousand
bitcoin
it's just a number uh how do you know
what's the value it's
there is no value at the moment in the
sense of catalytic value
uh because there were no prices
established yet
and so i think it's a change in behavior
that people started this kind of
artistic collection where you say
oh that's a cool experiment i'd somehow
get it that it's limited
uh that there's a limited amount coming
as a supply
and i think it's in a way it's nicer to
have more of that like like a
collectible card
of something and i'm and then it adds
this kind this resilience of this
experiment this added
monetary network effect uh demand
and so on and then it's basically
history that's the same with gold why do
we have such high stock to flow in gold
it's
it's not an objective law that tells you
due to physics gold must have the stock
to flow ratio no
it's due to the history of human beings
acting upon their subjective means and
assessment they tended to hold on to
more gold than
other assets which led to a historical
stock
of course linked their link you have the
objective criterion of durability which
made that possible
uh to have increasing stocks over time
uh so that
gold has the highest stock to flow ratio
and that's a pattern that's something
more objective it's inter-subjective
yeah that's the term here it's not
entirely arbitrary it's not by chance
gold has not a different physical
quality
only that's not that interesting to the
economist has a different economic
quality
it has different stock to flow ratio
but not to anything due to anything
intrinsic in gold due to a process a
historic process
of people holding on and gathering more
gold and increasing stocks
and caring about stocks
and something similar happened with
bitcoin
that's why you have this doctor flow
ratio in bitcoin it's not something
objective coming out of bitcoin
it's the link between objective
properties of the technology
and the subjective assessment of people
and the catalytic self-reinforcement
in the social interaction and exchange
that is the drive of the increasing
stock to flow ratio
of bitcoin
[Music]
of course you have the limiting flow and
that's one important
aspect which shares it shares with gold
is increasing marginal cost of
production
and that's by chance uh is
the reason or the most important
physical property for gold is there
the increasing marginal cost of
production
and the reason for that is the way gold
is distributed in the earth's surface
it's distributed right the way that the
the first goal is fairly easy and then
doesn't take a lot of costs you have it
in rivers
and so on the first layer but the more
gold you try to extract from the earth
the more costly it becomes and that has
held
on uh throughout history it may change
once we have the asteroid mining
in case that may we don't know may
change
for now it wouldn't change because the
cost is extra is astronomically high
so it doesn't matter but there could be
a point in future where the costs
of extracting gold is decreasing and for
most
goods the marginal cost of production is
decreasing you have economies of scale
with gold you don't have economies of
scale
and with bitcoin due to its
technological algorithmic construction
has the same pattern
of increasing costs of production due to
the mining difficulty
but but i would say that this is not
always the case in bitcoin because what
would have happened if theoretically
satoshi were the only one to continue
mining
and he's always using the same shitty
laptop to do so right then the
difficulty would not
adjust so the the interesting thing in
bitcoin is
is that the rate of the cost for the
rate of production
increases as more entrepreneurs try to
increase the production
of bitcoin yeah
yeah but it's similar with gold
if no one cares about gold and it's very
cheap to extract
it's the first deposits of gold
are almost costless to get them
yes but for example you could also have
said that in bitcoin um
like at genesis blog if we already would
have had asic
machines and such and such right then
the difficulty would very
very very quickly increase so the
production rate
would be very costly yeah and then again
if miners shut off it would get easier
over time
so it's it's a bit different that it
depends not so much on the
on the past work done by other
entrepreneurs but rather about the
current work done
maybe but you know as you said in gold
if if some entrepreneurs pick up the
gold from the riverbed
well then it's gonna get more difficult
while in bitcoin it's more like
how many people are digging for the gold
right now and that adjusts how difficult
it is
yeah i'm not sure that this difference
is important i would still say for gold
increased cost of production is due to
competition usually of
more people one of mining one to mine
so it's similar but yeah of course i
mean it's never the same it's just an
analogy and of course the
technologically it's a very different
beast that we have here
yeah so a good point
i think you realize
the nuance difference between those two
things is uh when you think through us
as people value gold
um entrepreneurs are incentivized to
produce new gold and then sell it on the
market right so the supply
of the gold increases um and then uh
yeah and then but in the market price
then uh the
the exchange ratio of gold goes down
while with bitcoin as more people value
bitcoin
more miners enter the field and
then the the supply rate change
does not change right it's because of
the difficulty adjustment the the
supply of bitcoin stays constant
regardless of how many entrepreneurs are
there
so there is simply no um
down pressure uh because of that
increase of
production rate that we see in gold
which is not present in bitcoin
yeah i still fundamentally i think is
very similar
that the results are similar but i agree
that
dynamic is a bit different
yeah but you you argue that it's even
better than gold for that reason
which may be true historically it has
held for a very long time that you have
increasing gold prices increasing
the incentives for mining and present
mining and increases the competition
in the mining sector and drives out
sub-marginal miners
which is a very similar kind of dynamic
happening but of course the details are
different
but you may be right i dare i can't
argue with you i don't know it may turn
out in the future that that's the
movement that's more sustainable
than the dynamics in the mining sector
maybe another way to highlight this is
that with bitcoin
like the the actual increase of the
money supply
is defined per block right
and then the it's more that
miners produce blocks and get paid newly
printed bitcoin so to say
rather than the miners actually
producing uh
the bitcoin itself um maybe that's
that's part of the analysis but i'm not
sure i can make the circle to provide a
compelling argument
okay well thanks i i propose we
go on and i think we'll fairly soon wrap
up
uh always almost 11 o'clock
and i'm really sweating a lot uh not due
to a challenging questions
it's really great points well due to the
heat wave here
so any any other question final remarks
uh final disagreements uh
yeah i guess we should wrap up thank you
if maybe one last question or comment if
anybody has
one
okay not then thanks again
thank you thanks for the great questions
and
great points it was a pleasure meeting
you
thank you very much for coming and and
and yeah so if someone wants to stay
around stay around
uh have a chat and
and seriously this this was great this
this was
this was really great uh anyone who
listened
to this we'll learn a lot from this
so yeah thank you guys and have a good
good night i agree
yeah two people you can you you can you
can stick around if you like in the
chats here or in the
3d world but otherwise i guess rahim
really wants to wants to refresh
what should get some refreshments okay
thanks a lot good night
good night everyone good night